Bates College Clothing Archive
Bates College Clothing Archive
1840 1940
1870 1920
23 boxes
157 garments
Bates College Clothing Archive Department of Theater and Dance 95 Nichols St Lewiston, ME 04240
Items in this collection are available study by request only. Items do not circulate and may only be used under supervision of Professor B. Christine McDowell in the costume storage building.
The Bates College Clothing Archive (BCCA) is a research and study collection of historical clothing owned by Bates College in Lewiston, Maine. The collection spans from roughly 1840 to 1930. We hold a collection of clothing owned by the family of Harry W. Rowe, Bates College's first Dean of Faculty, as well as items belonging to Barbara Wiggin of Lewiston, Maine, all from 1910 to 1940. Our collection is strongest, however, in late nineteenth century middle-class women's clothing, such as day bodices, skirts, and outerwear.
Most items in this collection are of unknown provenance, and were donated to the Bates Department of Theater and Dance with the intention of being used as theatrical costumes. The collection was processed by Grace Acton during the 2023-2024, in partial fulfillment of an Honors Thesis in Interdisciplinary Studies.
Clothing and dress History; Costume; Dress accessories
- Rowe Family Collection, 1840 1940; Rowe Family; Wilson Ruth Rowe 1914-2012; Rowe Eleanor Hope Chandler 1887-1972; Rowe Harry Willison 1887-1980; Wilson Valentine Haining 1915-1964 Val; 3 boxes; 23 garments
  Four members of the Rowe family -- Eleanor Hope Chandler Rowe, her husband Harry Willison Rowe, their daughter Ruth Rowe Wilson, and her husband Valentine "Val" Haining Wilson -- were attendees of Bates College, and remained involved with the College for decades after their studies. Harry was the College's first Dean of Faculty, serving from 1946-1958, and Ruth was the editor the _Bates Magazine_ from 1964-1980.
  Eleanor Hope Chandler was born in Presque Isle, Maine in 1887. She attended Bates College, matriculating with the Class of 1912, but did not complete her Bachelor's Degree. While at Bates, she met her husband, Harry Willison Rowe, born in 1887 in Mercer, Maine, and the two married on September 2, 1913 at Hope's family home in Presque Isle.
  Harry was hired by Bates College in 1914 as the Secretary of the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA). Over the next 44 years, Harry would hold a variety of positions in the Bates College administration, including Bursar, Alumni Secretary, Assistant to President Clifton Dagget Gray, and, starting in 1946, the College's first Dean of Faculty. Hope and Harry lived adjacent to the College, and Hope frequently acted as a chaperone for campus events. The Rowes had three children: Ruth, born in 1914, Robert, born in 1916, and Esther, born in 1917. Following his retirement in 1958, Harry became the first unofficial archivist and historian of Bates College.
  Ruth Rowe followed in her parents' footsteps and likewise attended Bates College, where she was highly involved in campus life as a reporter for the student newspaper, a competitive debater, President of the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA), choir singer, and Winter Carnival committee member. At Bates, she met her husband, Valentine "Val" Wilson, and the two were chosen to represent the college at the international convention of the Student Volunteer Movement in 1935. Ruth graduated in 1936 and Val in 1938; the two married in Gomes Chapel on August 25, 1939. Val went on to have a successful career as a Baptist minister and higher education leader, becoming Vice President of the Colorado Woman's College in 1950 and President of Skidmore College in 1957. Ruth and Val were noted for taking personal interest in the lives of students, and had six children of their own: David, Carol, Alden, Nancy, Kathryn, and James
  - Women's Garments, 1 box; 13 garments (Box 1E.1)
    This series consists of clothing designed to be worn by adult women, including Eleanor Hope Chandler Rowe and Ruth Rowe Wilson, as well as the family's ancestors.
    - Ancestors' Apparel, 1840 1900; 1900; 4 garments
      Contains garments belonging to Rowe family ancestors which predate Hope Chandler's adulthood.
      - Bodice, 1900; BCCA2024.03.01; 1 bodice
        Black satin bodice with lace overlay.
      - Skirt, 1900; BCCA2024.03.02; 1 skirt
        Black satin skirt.
      - Cap, 1900; BCCA2024.03.03; 1 cap
        Black satin cap.
      - Bodice, 1840 1850; BCCA2024.03.04; 1 bodice
        Brown wool bodice with off-white repeating print.
    - Hope's Rose Dress and Accessories, 1939; 3 garments
      n ensemble worn by Hope Chandler Rowe to the wedding of her daughter, Ruth Rowe Wilson.
      - Dress, 1939; BCCA2024.03.05; 1 dress
        Pink lace dress.
      - Gloves, 1939; BCCA2024.03.06; 1 pair of gloves
        Pair of purple knit gloves.
      - Sash or cummerbund, 1939; BCCA2024.03.07; 1 sash
        Sash or cummerbund in pink chiffon.
    - Hope's Wedding Underwear, 1913; 4 garments
      Contains two sets of coordinated chemises and drawers which were described by the donor as Hope's "wedding underwear".
      - Chemise, 1913; BCCA2024.03.12; 1 chemise
        White cotton chemise embroidered with "EHC" monogram.
      - Drawers, 1913; BCCA2024.03.13; 1 pair of drawers
        White cotton drawers embroidered with "EHC" monogram.
      - Chemise, 1913; BCCA2024.03.14; 1 chemise
        White linen chemise with cutwork embroidery.
      - Drawers, 1913; BCCA2024.03.15; 1 pair of drawers
        White linen drawers with cutwork embroidery.
    - Additional, 1920; 2 garments
      Additional garments likely worn by Hope Chandler Rowe or Ruth Rowe Wilson.
      - Veil, 1910 1950; BCCA2024.03.16; 1 veil
        Ivory tulle wedding veil. Possibly worn by Hope Chandler (married 1913) or Ruth Rowe (married 1939).
      - Cocktail dress, 1920; BCCA2024.03.18; 1 dress
        Beige satin dress with beaded overlay and braided trim.
  - Children's Garments, 1 box; 5 garments; Rowe Esther (Box 1F.3)
    This series consists of clothing in appropriate sizes for children aged 0-6. The donor described these items as being worn by Ruth Rowe Wilson and Esther Rowe as children, and some are likely created from passed-down clothing items.
    - Child's dress, 1915; BCCA2024.03.19; 1 dress
      White cotton dress with lace trim taken from an earlier petticoat.
    - Child's trousers, 1920; BCCA2024.03.20; 1 pair of trousers
    - Child's smock dress, 1920; BCCA2024.03.21; 1 dress
      Child's smock-style dress in cotton fabric with print of ducks.
    - Child's tunic, 1915; BCCA2024.03.22; 1 tunics
      Child's cotton gingham tunic.
    - Child's shorts, 1915; BCCA2024.03.23; 1 pair of shorts
      Child's cotton gingham shorts.
  - Bathing Suits, 1 box; 4 garments (Box 1E.3)
    This series consists of wool knit bathing suits which were noted by the donor as belonging to Eleanor Hope Chandler.
    - Bathing suit, 1921; BCCA2024.03.08; 1 bathing suit
      Solid black wool knit bathing suit.
    - Bathing suit, 1920; BCCA2024.03.09; 1 bathing suit
      Solid navy wool knit bathing suit.
    - Bathing suit, 1920; BCCA2024.03.10; 1 bathing suit
      Dark gray wool knit with stripes of purple, green, and peach.
    - Bathing suit, 1920; BCCA2024.03.11; 1 bathing suit
      Navy wool knit with green trim.
  - Provenance Documents, Available only as digital images. Originals were disposed of due to concern of acidity and pest infestation.; 15 JPEG images
    Notes written on or enclosed within cardboard boxes used to deliver and store the Rowe Family Collection. Likely written by Ruth Rowe Wilson or Hope Chandler Rowe. Photographs produced by Grace Acton.
- General Collection, 1840 1940
  The general collection encompasses all garments not contained within the Rowe Family collections.
  - Outerwear, 1860 1930; 20 Outerwear garments
    This series represents outerwear garments designed for all genders, including coats, dusters, jackets, and shawls.
    - Coats, 6 Coats
    - Capes, 7 Capes
    - Jackets, 6
    - Shawl, 1850; BCCA2023.11.03; 1 Shawl
      Lace
  - Dresses
    - Wedding Dresses, 1920 1927; 1 box (Box 2B.1)
      Wedding costume.
      - Wedding dress, 1927; BCCA2024.02.01; 1 Wedding dress
        Ivory silk wedding dress with full lace overlay and long train.
      - Wedding dress, 1920; BCCA2024.04.01; 1 Wedding dress; Wiggin Barbara
        Ivory satin wedding dress.
    - Day Dresses, 1850 1925; 11 Day dresses (Box 1C.3, Box 1E.1, Box 1E.2, Box 2A.3, Box 2B.2, Box 2C.1)
      This sub-series encompasses dresses designed to be worn in the morning and/or afternoon. The 11 garments span from 1850 to 1925, and represent a variety of materials and styles.
  - Bodices, 1845 1900; 36 Bodices (Box 1A.1, Box 1C.2, Box 1D.1, Box 1E.1, Box 2A.1, Box 2B.2)
    Bodices (women's garments for the upper body) comprise a large portion of the General Collection. The collection reflects the transition from separate bodices and skirts to one-piece dresses, which took place in the early 20th century. The Bodices series represent styles typical of middle-class New England women, and are constructed mostly of wool and silk fabrics.
  - Skirts